Guide to the Small Collections in the James Weldon Johnson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Small Collections in the James Weldon Johnson collection
1850-1976
JWJ MSS SMALL COLLECTIONS
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
3 boxes
Correspondence, writings, memorabilia by and relating to Romare Bearden; Augusta Bird Courtney; Frederick Douglass; Alexandre Dumas, père and fils; Paul Laurence Dunbar; Rudolph Dunbar; Elsie Taylor DuTrieuille; Jack Flodin; Mifflin Wistar Gibbs; Angelina W. Grimké; Georgia Douglas Johnson; Le Roi Jones; Alain LeRoy Locke; Edgar Mittelholzer; Arthur Alfonso Schomburg; George Samuel Schuyler; Harriet Beecher Stowe; Booker T. Washington; and Frank Yerby.
James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters (Yale University)
Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988
Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1878-1962
Courtney, Augusta Bird
Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895
Dumas, Alexandre, 1802-1870
Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895
Dunbar, Paul Laurence, 1872-1906
Dunbar, Rudolph
DuTrieuille, Elsie Taylor
Flodin, Jack
Grimké, Angelina Weld, 1880-1958
Johnson, Georgia Douglas, 1886-1966
Baraka, Amiri, 1934-2014
Locke, Alain, 1885-1954
Mittelhölzer, Edgar, 1909-1965
Schomburg, Arthur Alfonso, 1874-1938
Schuyler, George S. (George Samuel), 1895-1977
Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1811-1896
Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915
Yerby, Frank, 1916-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Small collections of correspondence writings and other material by or pertaining to African-American writers and other cultural figures, forming part of the James Weldon Johnson Collection.
African American authors -- 19th century -- Archives; African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters (Yale University)
- BEARDEN, ROMARE, n.d.
  - Caresse, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    To: 0 / From: 1
  - Untitled, circular with colorprint (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - inscribed to Mrs. J. W. Johnson, n.d.
  - Untitled, article concerning Bearden's (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Passion", handwritten
- BONTEMPS, ARNA
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 6)
- BRAITHWAITE, WILLIAM STANLEY
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 72)
- COURTNEY, AUGUSTA BIRD, 1934
  - Ikerd, L. W., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    To: 1 / From: 0
  - Flint, Margaret V., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hunt, H. A., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence with David I., 1933-34 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Walsh
    includes carbon of letter from
    James Weldon Johnson to Walsh
  - Untitled children's story, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    typed manuscript with corrections
- CULLEN, COUNTEE
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 7)
- DODSON, OWEN
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS Dodson)
- DOUGLASS, FREDERICK
  - Correspondence
    - Barnside, J. A. P., 1869 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Mr. Cook, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Coster, Robert, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Mrs. Dorsey, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Fortune, T. Thomas, 1883-89 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      To: 0 / From: 4
    - [Greenwood, Grace], 1887 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Higginson, Thomas W., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Johnson, Robert, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Mr. Koehler, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - L. Praug and Co., 1873 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Reynolds, F. H. C., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Unidentified correspondents, 1863-84 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      To: 0 / From: 3
    - Unidentified correspondents (Box 1, Folder 46)
      (n.b. only 2 letters in folder)
    - Autographs and photos, 1881, 1893, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- DUBOIS, W. E. B.
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 8)
- DUMAS, ALEXANDRE père
  - Bocage, [Pierre Tousez], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    To: 0 / From: 2
  - Granger, jeweler, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Guerville, 18--? Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Hostein, [Hippolyte?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Nodier, Charles, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Prefect of Seine et Oise, 1850 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, letters to, 1857 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - unidentified correspondents, 1857 Oct 9, n.d.
    To: 0 / From: 6
  - "Chronique du 19", autograph manuscript of article (3 p.) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - "Cour d'assise de Naples", autograph manuscript of article (4 p.) (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "De la necessité d'un port franc aux manuscript of article (7 p.) (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "L'Autonomie Napolitaine", autograph manuscript of article (6 p.) (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - "La colonne des Martyres", autograph manuscript of article (2 p.) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "La Vice Royauté de Naples", autograph manuscript of article (7 p.) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "Le Journal Napoli et l'Emeute de Ste. Lucie", autograph manuscript of article (4 p.) (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - "Le Spectre de M. Conforti", autograph manuscript of article (2 p.) (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - "Les bouts rimés", autograph manuscript of article in letter form (5 p., p. 2 missing) (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - "Naples et Marseille", autograph manuscript of article (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - "Pompeia", autograph manuscript of article (6 p.) (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - "Prédictions réalisées", autograph manuscript of article (3 p.) (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - "Victor Hugo", autograph manuscript of article (2 p.) (Box 1, Folder 67)
- DUMAS, ALEXANDRE fils
  - Correspondence, letters to unidentified (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - correspondents
    To: 0 / From: 5
  - Correspondence, letters to unidentified, 1892 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - correspondents
  - Autograph and photograph (Box 1, Folder 70)
- DUNBAR, PAUL LAURENCE
  - Correspondence, Alice Dunbar-Nelson to William F. Gable. 1 letter (photostat), 1915, includes photostat of one of Dunbar's poems (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence, Alice Dunbar-Nelson to, 1926, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Helen R. London (2 letters)
  - "On the Death of John Hay", poem, handwritten manuscript (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - "Possum", poem, handwritten manuscript (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Untitled, autographed poem (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Catalog of Dunbar papers in the Ohio State Archeological and Historical Society in Columbus, Ohio (Box 2, Folder 75a)
    Includes: facsimiles of some papers
- DUNBAR, RUDOLPH
  - Invitations and telegrams to Dunbar (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Coleridge, Taylor, Avril (letters to Dunbar) (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Still, William Grant (letters to Dunbar) (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Letters to Dunbar removed from a scrapbook, 1943, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 78a)
    (From Brendan Bracken and
    unidentified)
- DuTRIEUILLE, ELSIE TAYLOR, 1937, 1942
  - Correspondence: letter from James, 1937, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Weldon Johnson to Carl Van Vechten
  - "Ode to Celestial Voices", dramatic poem, mimeographed (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - "Plymouth, An Allegory", carbon copy, "For Those Who March, in Memory of the Spirit of the Late James Weldon Johnson" (Box 2, Folder 81)
    handwritten note re: Toussaint
    L'Ouverture Society
- FLODIN, JACK, 1946
  - Johnson, Mrs. James Weldon, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - "Girl of Fifteen", musical setting for James Weldon Johnson's poem, manuscript "The Glory of the Day Was In Her Face" (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Ditto copies of several musical arrangements (Box 2, Folder 84)
    Includes "Girl of Fifteen Years"
- GIBBS, MIFFLIN WISTER
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 20)
- GRIMKE, ANGELINA W., 1936
  - Jackman, Harold, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Autograph, "In Memory of Archibald Grimke", poem, handwritten manuscript (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - "Hushed by the Hands of Sleep," poem, typescript (Box 2, Folder 90a)
- HURSTON, ZORA NEALE
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 9)
- JOHNSON, GEORGIA DOUGLAS
  - Correspondence
    - Jackman, Harold, 1936-42 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      To: 0 / From: 12
    - Johnson, James Weldon, 1929-34 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      To: 1 / From: 3
  - Writings
    - "Brotherhood Marching Song", song (Box 2, Folder 93)
      dittoed
    - "Frederick Douglass", one act play (Box 2, Folder 94)
      carbon copy
    - "Interracial", poem, dittoed (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - "Plumes", one act play, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 96)
      manuscript
    - "The Starting Point", one act play (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - "Tomorrow's World", song by Georgia D. Johnson and Lillian Evanti, mimeograph (Box 2, Folder 98)
- JONES, LE ROI
  - Correspondence
    - Loewinsohn, Ron, 1958-63, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 99)
      To: 0 / From: 22
  - Writings
    - The Baptism, a comedy in one act (Box 2, Folder 100)
      mimeographed
    - The Toilet, a play in one act (Box 2, Folder 101)
- LOCKE, ALAIN
  - Correspondence
    - Cullen, Countee, 1928 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 101a)
    - DeWitt, Josephine, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Jackman, Harold, 1924-38 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Writings
    - "The Negro in the Three Americas: Race, Culture, and Democracy" (Box 2, Folder 104)
      inaugural lecture in series called The Negro's Contribution to the Culture of the Americas, typed
      manuscript with revisions
    - "The Poetry of Negro Life", preface to Four Negro Poets (Box 2, Folder 105)
      handwritten manuscript
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Zora Neale Hurston, The Chick With One Hen.
- MITTELHOLZER, EDGAR
  - Correspondence
    - Markoe, F. H., 1952, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Writings
    - "At Forty-Three-A Personal View of the World" (Box 2, Folder 107)
      typed manuscript
    - "At Forty-Three: A Personal View of the World" (Box 2, Folder 108)
      excerpts
- PETERSON, DOROTHY
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 10)
- SCHOMBURG, ARTHUR A., n.d.
  - Jackman, Harold, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Megelin, Oscar, 1915-16 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    To: 2 / From: 0
  - Veith, Paul F., 1935-39 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    and letters re: Schomburg
    To: 8 / From: 0
  - Review of James Weldon Johnson's Black Manhattan, typed (Box 2, Folder 112)
- SCHUYLER, GEORGE S., 1933
  - ---- Jones (photocopy), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - "Remarks G. S. Schuyler at the 80th, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Birthday Dinner for Carl Van Vechten", typed
  - "Remarks G. S. Schuyler at the 75th, [1955] (Box 2, Folder 114a)
  - Birthday Dinner for Carl Van Vechten", typescript carbon
  - [Critical commentary written for the reprint of Van Vechten's Nigger Heaven ], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 114b)
  - "The Van Vechten Revolution," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 114c)
- SCHUYLER, JOSEPHINE, 1946, n.d.
  - Poems, typescript, 1946, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 114)
    Includes: "October," "A Saga of Songs
    for Philippa [Prelude]," and
    "Lililies of Our Valley"
- SPINGARN, JOEL
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 11)
- STOWE, HARRIET BEECHER, 1865
  - Mr. Bonner (damaged), 1865 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Lady Hutherton, Aug 22, n.y. (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Mr. Underwood, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Typed excerpts from "A Narrative of Sojourner Truth" by H. B. Stowe, autograph (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - [Autograph quotation from the Bible (Psalm 37:3)], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 118a)
- THURMAN, WALLACE
  (Material now cataloged as JWJ MSS 12)
- WASHINGTON, BOOKER T.
  - Correspondence
    - Albany Times-Union, to the editor, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 119)
    - Alexander, Charles, 1904-05 (Box 3, Folder 120)
      Extracts from letters from BTW
    - Beers, Le Grand, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 121)
    - Dodson, N. B., 1912 (Box 3, Folder 122)
    - Edgerton, Sata T., 1900 (Box 3, Folder 123)
    - Farnum, Henry W., 1915 (Box 3, Folder 124)
    - Fortune, T. Thomas, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - Garrison, Francis J., 1899-1908 (Box 3, Folder 126)
      To: 0 / From: 33
    - Holt, Hamilton, 1901-09 (Box 3, Folder 127)
      To: 1 / From: 11
    - Jacoby, Henry S., 1907 (Box 3, Folder 128)
    - Lord, Mrs. ---, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 129)
      Includes photo of BTW
    - Luke, Arthur F., 1901 (Box 3, Folder 130)
    - Meyer, Isaac, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 131)
    - Milbank, Albert J., 1903 (Box 3, Folder 132)
    - Moody, Paul D., 1915 (Box 3, Folder 133)
    - Moore, [Fred R.], 1904 (Box 3, Folder 134)
      Includes letter to R. C. M. Simmons
      from Emmett J. Scott
    - Nast, Thomas, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 135)
    - New York Independent, to the editor
      See: Holt, Hamilton, Box 3, folder 127
    - New York Times, to the editor, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 136)
    - Ovington, Mary White, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 137)
    - Peterson, Jerome B.
      To: 0 / From: 0
    - Peterson, Jerome B., 1903 (Box 3, Folder 138)
      See also: Fortune, T. Thomas, Box 3, folder 125
    - Pierrepont, John Jay, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 139)
    - Schener, Florence, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - Simmons, R. C. M.
      See: Moore, [Fred. R.], Box 3, folder 134
    - Thomas, M. L., 1896 (Box 3, Folder 141)
    - 6 checks signed by BTW, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - Fragment of letter by BTW, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 143)
    - Eulogy for BTW by Unidentified, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 143a)
    - Signature, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 143b)
      [Removed from first edition of Up From Slavery ]
- YERBY, FRANK, 1944-45
  - Cousins, John S., 1944-45 (Box 3, Folder 144)
    (from Cousins = typed copies)
    To: 1 / From: 2
  - Six poems, typed and handwritten (Box 3, Folder 145)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence
  Miscellaneous Correspondence formerly listed here has been transferred to a separate list: James Weldon Johnson Collection Files (JWJ MSS FILE).